all right welcome to our sixth solution
right we've done five other ones and
this is our one on labor and what is
raising is its we spend I'm just going
to meet you for a second marks might be
yours that's chirping at me we spend an
hour having a conversation to generate
solutions for a specific area to spend
15 minutes talking about what it looks
like right now in society this is
normally what we concentrate on it
clearly takes a lot longer than 15
minutes to figure out what's good and
bad about transportation or in this case
labor but because we concentrate on it
so much in society I just get 15 minutes
to kind of recap what we all all know
and think about it with the pandemic and
can sometimes take a little longer than
15 minutes because things have changed
and so it's not the same old same old we
talked about and then we spend 15
minutes talking about our version of an
amazing future however foreign that in
the distance you need to be five ten a
hundred years and then we spend the vast
majority the time the 30 minutes talking
about what is an adjacent possible what
is something we could do right now if we
had 10,000 people and $100,000 that
would help us in this case in the area
of labor so I will unmute you now mark
and I'll let Alejandra onion herself
wants to and if you want to know what do
you see happening right now with labor
mark well it's I see a lot of fear I've
been on a couple of meditation groups
and there was a couple of people who
were actually you could see them their
face they were terrified about the the
possibility that they wouldn't have
money coming in next week to pay for the
rest their new stuff so I I definitely
come at the other end of the spectrum
I see like a manufacturer in kitchener
mobilizing to retool laser cutters and
3d printers to make face masks reusable
face masks
- the doctor specifications and they're
making something like 8,000 a day now so
and they're employing people from all
over so that that mean there's something
there there's an opportunity there and
of course they're making money but he
talked about he talked about making
money in an almost apologetic way as if
to say well this has to be good for
everyone
and I really like the sound of that to
me that's that's kind of like the answer
to the to the what is the fear and the
feeling of hopelessness that I see from
some of the people is these kind of
novel solutions where the people who
create the company or the corporation
have kind of like an internal guide that
says we only need to make this much
money as a matter of fact we don't want
to make any more money if there's a
possibility that we can employ others
and this our solution will go viral no
matter what it is it'll go viral
people will see it's sustainable and
growing and good for everyone and want
to get in the cause so I see that as an
opportunity like lately but I need some
notes because some sometimes they do
sometimes they don't and so like I said
like before I started these solution
raisings and slightly a coke in nineteen
free world where although it was still
happy in Japan of Japan
I'm so happy in China and it was spread
it wasn't um yet as as close to us in
North America as it is now and so I've
been thinking about labor for years of
the things that I'm gonna mention aren't
necessarily related to to the pandemic
but at the same time they are because
they're why everyone is so stressed
right now and why we have to that
labor right now is basically trading
your time for money and so you're on
your own you have to find a job trade
your time for money and then you use
that money to get your needs met to put
a roof over your head and food on the
table where you and your family
CL Hendra and now has her join her back
in and even people who are working
extremely hard can't seem to make ends
meet and yet there's people who have
useless jobs who make millions and
millions of dollars who their the thing
they are doing isn't actually
contributing to society in any real way
about making anything up with new
inventions they're just trading digits
they're speculating on the market or
feeding off of other people's labor and
they're not they're not able and I mean
really truly or not employed people
they're just it isn't fair like people
some people have to trade their time for
money and other people entrepreneurs or
take high risks to make money and now
we're seeing that falling apart too with
the people who are high risk tolerance
they don't have money saves they can't
make payroll they can't pay their leases
I can't so all of these businesses are
going under and you're losing jobs and
everyone's seen how our jobs are the way
we get all of our needs met
it's the way we have our sense of
purpose and there isn't enough to go
around especially right now right
there's only so many essential services
they can employ people and yet everyone
still has rents everyone still has all
of these um all of these expenses to pay
stage and you see me move in my head
it's just I'm trying to tilt it back and
forth I'm not responding I'm not saying
yeah I know it's already you first got
my note cuz it's like a mirror it's the
mirror effect and so Alejandra do you
have anything to add to what Labour
currently looks like for you or in the
world whether pre Kovac or Korea yeah
this is also something that I've been
thinking about for a while and I lived
in Europe for every time in Holland and
where things were very good and I live
in and I am from Argentina and now I'm
here in Ghana status from since 2011
reality so I'm sort of in contact with
both realities and and one of the things
that I've started seeing already when I
was in Holland and is that okay you can
have organized labor and in such a way
that it works for mostly everybody that
there is not enough work or they were to
go around for everybody but you can have
some sort of system that keeps that
order in place when you come to Latin
America that is not there and and then
you have people at work
a structural poverty and and an other
type of social plan doesn't need to be
put in place in order to contain them
their problem we already see that there
is not enough for everybody because of
the way that is structured and and there
is also something out there and I see is
that in any to that point that you were
making there is a mismatch between money
value and wealth so those concepts are
sometimes used as placeholders for one
another but they are not the same so you
get money from some service that you
provide and that service or that good
that you provide might have value or not
and what we see is a lot of money the
import into things that do not represent
real value for the people or society so
it's just like you know the financial
and creating more money for money and
and that is also not necessarily
representative of the wealth that you
might have as as a person because the
wealth is also represented by your
network but your the quantity of the air
that you breathe and all other things so
where labor comes in is in one specific
area that is the means in order to get
the what what do you need to cover your
needs not only the physical and material
needs but also a psychological emotional
and self-realization
so I see that as as there's there's a
broken system but we know that it's not
is not sustainable in time the gig
economy is also not a good solution for
that it has to slowly start drifting to
a different paradigm which now has been
accelerated by the whole crisis and the
whole crisis what is producing and also
not this crisis but also the the whole
scalable age that is already coming and
now it's being sort of catalyzed by the
corona crisis is this this new way of
collaboration that also produces a lot
of displacement and the sectors that are
displaced are not necessarily the ones
that are easier to absorb so is this
very very tricky situation in which were
in that this long time coming is in my
eyes is not new but now it's being
accelerated and that's one of the things
that worries me the most about this
whole new situation because we're gonna
see the effects of these coming in the
next few months and it will last for a
long time and they need to be solutions
in place to start absorbing and
redirecting labor into in ways that are
sustainable and and useful for everybody
so that's why I'm I just wanted to
mention we only have a few more minutes
to discuss this portion so now we can
still open up now that everyone's had a
reason a chance to share my brain is not
on point today but I wanted to share
this picture that I drew I drew that I
drew this I draw this picture a lot it's
when I've sat with with forum so for
something to get done in our society you
need one individual to have all three of
these things the desire to do the task
the awareness to do the task and the
skill to do it right the wareness of
this that the task needs to get done and
in society the only one we really care
about is that people don't desire to do
the task so we pay them to do it but it
doesn't actually get them the same level
of
Venis that if they had truly desired to
do the task without being paid for it
the other two are much easier to deal
with I'm just gonna put this down now if
you're not skilled in the task you just
need training and the one that our
society doesn't focus on at all is that
if you both want to do the task and are
trained to do the task which is
happening right now in the world or
people are like I know how to make
respirator masks I know how to do 3d
printing I am aware this thing needs to
get done but I don't know where to put
it and and that can be an easy
technological fix something that is just
a platform of hey this task needs to get
done do you have the skill of the desire
here is the awareness that is it is
getting done because I think with labor
there's the - there's the economic part
that we need things done and I've never
seen what what truly is an essential
service that needs to happen in our
economies for our economies to function
for our world to function and then
there's the individual piece which is
like we want to have a sense of purpose
and get our needs met right we need food
we need we need and so to some degree I
like teasing those two apart to say how
do we get those both met without it all
being this complex menagerie of I don't
know complexity but that it falls apart
it's like wait not everyone's job is
necessary but people are necessary they
still need to get fed they still need to
get clothed and housed so yeah anyone
else having
rapping up thoughts for this section on
how the world currently works before we
get to shift into the beautiful version
of the future that doesn't need to match
but can be anything we want it to be in
this in this realm of getting stuff done
in our economy and individually well
I'll say one thing I've been involved in
a couple of creating initiatives I was
involved on Barney's business unit here
in Moose Jaw they do a neo flight
training
that's what countries from all over the
world calling the important Britain and
Italy that are in NATO and they they
came out with this achieving excellence
program as a way to engage their
employees and it was it was really well
researched it was just not well
delivered so was as if they were
recognizing that a better way to do
things was to create an awareness and a
desire in their in their employees and
and leverage that with the company's
mission and vision but there was some
disconnect they couldn't quite do it
there they didn't get the buy-in and
when they rolled it out they it was as
if the people who were rolling it out
were saying this is something we need to
do to please the bosses because we're
getting graded on this so there was a
disconnect but I was surprised but left
by the level of understanding somebody
connected the dots just to say that
somebody has to see where their work
matters they they have to know that
they're being listened to and there has
to be a way of a robust way of gathering
all of that information and kind of an
active listening way put it back to the
employee so it was it was like a great
great idea but the execution was flawed
so to me it's like there's that new way
of being is in there it's already in
there people recognize it they just
don't recognize it
level I'll say the worth of a machine
you know what they don't quite they
haven't quite raised it to that level so
to me that's promising you have any
closing thoughts for this section on how
the world currently works and no
actually I would say I thought it was
really interesting the graph that you
showed about skill and desire and which
is another and the other side of the
echo and you have value money and wealth
and then you on the other side of the
sort of like the structural situation
then from the perspective of the person
having the skill the desire and the
awareness and and also that led me to
think about the connection it's like
when you have the desire when you have
the this cure and the awareness why
don't what can't you get the job so that
filter there it's like right now we have
people that have all that meet all these
qualities but they need to go through
this funnel in order to be placed in
different and different positions so
that's one one one thing that came into
my mind when you were talking about that
right thank you
so now we can switch into our beautiful
version of the future in your ideal
world what would labor look like either
for you for the account for the world
the economy or for both sever would like
to start I have lots of thoughts on this
as well which is why I've been sitting
with this for so haha
go ahead Ben alright to me my version of
the future doesn't tie it together our
knee our needs and our desire to do to
contribute in the world I want every
human beings needs to be met and that
makes sure that they are fed and clothed
and housed and educated and connected
while at the same time fine you know
their unique contribution to the world
that may or may not be profitable may or
may not be something that other people
value to put money on right
you might be a teacher teaching someone
who can't afford the the tuition and so
separating the individuals needs making
sure those are met and then making sure
also that everything gets done within
society is dealing with that graph it's
instead of paying people finding the
people who wants to do the work if
someone wants to do the work they are
willing to do it for free if their needs
are met they don't need to necessarily
get paid if they want to if we don't
have enough skilled people to do it
making sure there's enough people going
through the education system for that
specific task and if they just aren't
aware that the task needs to get done
that is the simplest one as I said and
then where we've concentrated on that
we've let people have their they're
calling their unique contribution and
stuff just doesn't get done like we look
at the world when potholes aren't filled
then you start doing external motivation
and incentivization hopefully beyond
money in my perfect world where it's
maybe like you get a concert to your
favorite artists they they're sponsoring
pothole filling and people help fill
potholes or just asking what would get
you to want to fill a pothole what would
how many is it making it fun having
music live events there knowing how to
do it doing it one time in one time only
you're becoming skilled at it that
everyone has their unique sense of self
in that like what would bring it what
would make it fulfilling for them to do
those things and so for me I I want to
untie this this time exchanging your
time for money and instead having it be
a world where you're choosing what to do
with your time which I think does bring
you into your highest calling and
contribution and then your needs are
also being met efficiently with groups
of people and like I said incentive I've
seen externally when needed but not
starting they're not starting at that
place once the systems in place as
clearly this is in a world like we
couldn't do this right now in this world
but it is happening like right now there
are so many people doing good in the
world and they're doing it for free
they're you know artists that make
millions of dollars or putting on live
concert so in their living room because
what they want to do with their time and
teachers who are you know putting out
videos to to teach even if they weren't
doing that beforehand now that
you have the time and they already had
the skill they're willing to to step
into that into that role and so that is
a bit of my vision of what I would like
to see in 10 to 20 years and I don't
know if I've you good people okay I can
I meet you and then I think mark metered
himself right I have seen your thoughts
before you go they don't need to match
so you don't need to like this is
impossible for mine it's like the
version of the future what is your
vision of the future I that's great that
you mention it just like it turns out
that that I had similar thoughts in
terms of decoupling these money from
from meeting the needs in my ideal world
you wouldn't have to worry about shelter
and clothing and they've got basic cost
of education and making you know the end
of the month and groceries and things
like that like your needs should be met
and with whatever means necessary and
that should free you up to to think what
and and feel what what is right for you
what is your unique capacity I think
that is very very connected to education
which with how you brought up and what
what your possibilities hard to explore
and discover what is actually fulfilling
to you what you can do what you want to
do and you skill to know and bring that
to offer to other people in society and
that you don't need to get paid for that
you you do what you want and that it
will be ideal and then you can also
choose to collaborate way when you see
the need in and this idea brings of
actions they know this idea of passion
and then many people talk about you
should do well when you're passionate
about and that doesn't mean that it's
something that makes you necessarily
happy or completely fulfilled
sometimes passion is the drive to solve
that you believe in for example I think
that we should you know clean up this
river is something that you like to do
in reality like picking out garbage or
things like that no but something that
you really believe in so and that is the
other thing so it's like having your
your needs met being able to choose
without having to think about money or
making it to the end of month what you
want to do and how you want to
collaborate and that is more or less
what my ideal looks like that with their
opportunity to keep on learning to
always keep on learning improving
yourself because that that is in in in
contrast with what you might have now
that it's like you kind of stuck in a
road and and and then it's very
difficult to switch and that flexibility
when you decouple it from from from
money and having to to earn a paycheck
that opens up a whole world of new
facilities
bark what are your thoughts well okay so
y'all done alejandra yep okay
aye aye I like those I like the ability
to be to have all your needs met without
having to worry about going into a job
that you think sucks your soul is uh
I've done that for a little bit it
there's a lot of negative things that
come out of that just are not good for
anyone there are some good things I mean
there's something to be said for you
know that grit to be able to gold to do
something that you you dislike but you
stick with it and you grow and you
become something stronger than you
thought was possible
I think there's something to be said for
that but just the system of the way it
is now produces this this huge
inequalities and then just so I think
there has to be a different driver and
for me the the drivers that seems to
resonate for me is wanting to move
society forward wanting the best for me
my future sells my community and the
world with the knowledge being for me to
have my best experience I need everyone
else to be their best self if I no
matter what I do for myself if if I
become the richest person in the world
and everybody else is starving outside
me that's not my miss best experience in
the world
there really isn't you can feel it I can
just feel it in my body so I I would
like to see the generator where it is
that there is
fell sensing your body like a
participatory knowing that that person
who is homeless may have the solution
that helps us get through the next mess
period so it's not like I feel I said a
conscious a consciousness thing or a
conscience it's like I know there's
something that is risking my future in
my children's future
if I let somebody start to death and
fail to bring their brilliant potential
into the world so I'd like to see that
be the driver of and understanding that
the world needs to look like what you
both just described but the
understanding that it needs to be that
way for our best experience so if if
that was a generator then people would
find a way to make sure that that person
has the best opportunity to bring their
brilliance to the world while making
sure that everyone's fed and taken care
of so then that generator would I guess
some things the way of the living would
emerge out of that making sure
everything is taken care of so in my
perfect world everybody has that
awareness that if I see somebody in the
street that is struggling there is a
potential risk that that might be the
one grain of sand that tips the scales
towards hell rather than towards you
know just kind of paradise on earth that
where everybody's able to do the work
that thing
the that reflects their best self I
guess so to me that that world of that
would under girl the undergird of the
word the world of labour and allow all
those things to happen anyways I don't
know it's kind of out in left field
maybe but that's for me that's that's
the basic said that was the basics
behind when I looked at Bombardier as
achieving excellence that's the way I
looked at it when I chaired meetings
like I often would go to someone and ask
them if they had a dissenting opinion
trying to get to the heart of what was
behind their dissenting opinion with the
idea that this person might be the one
helping us to avoid disaster so then if
if we looked at everyone like that
especially the artists the artists you
can't monetize what they brave but you
want them to bring it even though it's
different from your vision you want them
to bring it because they might give you
something that you you know no other way
about of achieving enemies I don't know
of anything
spark you added a lot and I think that
that is a good you know the future is
where we do see the value in other human
beings every human being has Worth and
even if I'm acting selfishly the best
thing I can do for myself and my child
is to make sure everyone is looked after
for exactly the reason you said they
could be the solution and right now I'm
seeing a lot of extreme ableism and
ageism of like well we can't shut down
the economy for the people over 85 and
like whatever they already have
pre-existing conditions already putting
a lot of money into them and I believe
that those very people the the elders of
course have knowledge because they've
been here for longer than anyone else
but including the people who have
chronic illnesses
and and such have a different life
experience I know that is a big part of
why I'm doing what I'm doing in the
world and why I'm able to handle this
crisis so much better than a lot of
other people is because of my health
challenges and what I've been through
and so to lose that that what we look at
is the weak portion of our society when
in reality they're they might be
physically weak their immune system
might be weak their lungs might be weak
but they are not weak and they have so
much to give and they're theirs
we're gonna lose a lot I am gonna lose a
lot by other people you are gonna lose a
lot by other people dying who might
either people who solve cancer might be
the people who know how to clean up the
ocean it might be the people who are
just there for us and we're going
through a hard time and to honor that
that every human being has potential and
to allow that to to emerge is definitely
a part of my beautiful future anything
you'd like to add Alejandra or mark
before we go on to the ten the adjacent
possible right now I also feel to say
the same way in that respect like the
police they raelia that it has to be the
best the best possible situation for
everybody and no I don't like compassion
for an empathy for other people and and
also like if we have to collaborate on
everybody all together the better we
collectively are the better we can
progress together this is the part of
that scalability of the system like and
exponential technologies and exponential
problems and we have to consider the
whole and in this single person more
than could be like the tipping point it
could be that that person that has the
solution but that person is also very
good in and of itself and so I think
that's very very powerful what she said
mark and then I often think it's very
interesting this idea of wait and
because they they agreed and we struggle
and it helped us
calm maybe there is some other way maybe
maybe they the world lies imagine it
it's not it's ideal but it's not perfect
so there is always the potential for
transformation and and and and me maybe
there is struggle but it doesn't have to
be such a difficult one or not not the
level of difficulty and cruelty that we
might experience right now but I think
they we said something to be said about
quit and and and this related to to push
through something and come out better
and so that's something that I I take as
well to think about them and consider
thank you we both unmuted you at the
same time er there's a little there's a
little chirp on your ends when you're
not talking so that's why I keep muting
music oh yeah I just wanted to pick up
on what Alejandra said about there who
needs to be that struggle but there
doesn't need to be added in the level
Isis it's like allowing the caterpillar
to break its way out of the chrysalis so
it doesn't die if you help the
caterpillar to break out of the
chrysalis its wings don't become strong
enough and if the struggles and dies
it's a horrifying thing but at the same
time you don't want to pinch the
chrysalis so much that that the
butterfly never emerges so I think it's
an awareness of that not adding
malevolence to to a natural somebody's
natural journey which that happens every
day we see malevolence in our way and
and we inadvertently accurate like
everyone does some more than others some
but I think I like that drawing that
distinction I think that's so now we can
transition to the the last section which
is
creating the adjacent possible so what
could we create together that hopefully
no single one of us could create it by
ourselves like just the idea if we had
ten thousand people and a hundred
thousand dollars and created something
that was voluntary that was a natural
attractor that wasn't about enforcing
our desire for a perfect world on other
people but something we could create
that would bring bring people in and I
think that yeah
what could we create but 10,000 people
and $100,000 that helps in this position
either the the need for things to get
done in the economy that jobs that are
essential how do we get them done and or
how do we get people to fulfill their
purpose and their genius whether we
wanted to use those things art or
whether we want to and so it can be
solutions to any of it with all the
other solution raising it sound like we
stuck to one solution it's just like
popcorn this could be a possibility and
this could be a possibility that is
there for bird 10,000 people and
$100,000 they could be people in the
same city if that's necessary or they
could be people around the world how did
you come up with that number 10,000 um
just cuz it's a doable number it's not
catastrophic ly huge but it's enough
that you could create that $100,000 is
relatively easy it's not gonna be a high
risk for any single individual there and
it helps um like me coming up with
$100,000 would be next to impossible but
10,000 people coming up with a hundred
thousand isn't and ten thousand people
is not extreme it's not a pie in the sky
vision of utopian future finding 10,000
people who want to create a solution to
labor or food or transportation so that
is that it's like the starting point of
something is if you had a hundred
thousand of a million dollars I'd be
even better but but it's it's starting
from from this point what could you
create hmm
I am when you show your your diagram the
[Music]
ideas generating in my mind because your
pen alike naturally an idea facilitator
people facilitator connector the
connector neatly maybe you're more
naturally connected or something between
the two but what if the 10,000 people
was an extended version of the the
spirit that has tension in you right now
so driven by that same idea to connect
skill to awareness and desire and
provide a space where that could be
could be multiplied 10,000 times in in a
dynamic way where people around those
10,000 people in their own little
communities could see opportunities
where their skill and or where their
desire and awareness could have matched
a skill that they were already possessed
I think that's one way to use that
so not maybe not something maybe not the
labor right away
it could be labor right away but I think
it might be a very very powerful thing
if we could show people right now how
they might be useful right where they
are and do that can continue that on
into the future in such a way like that
guy in Kitchener Orla bats who's making
hand sanitiser
we've basically put the game a hoarders
out of business by saturating the market
with a free product because they they
see they have a desire and awareness and
they they have the skill and they just
put it out there and I think it can win
that's a very good natural attractive
people feel it deep down especially at a
time of this so if we could show people
where the opportunities are that might
be something that's just the first thing
that occurred to you
yeah I think that a lot of my ideas come
from this diagram like if we could help
people train right that's a platform
that's a tech platform that's quite easy
there if we could help people just know
what is out there that needs to get done
and if we can we can focus their desire
we don't and yet all of our current
gaming world is generally focused on how
do we create the desire so you want to
do this job how do we create the desire
for this product that you don't actually
want instead of visit is it like
uniquely yours to do and that makes it
sound like it has to be a grandiose you
know you'd have to know you're fit like
your purpose on the planet and your
genius before you can take a step
forward but it's it's what do you want
to do with this morning what do you want
to do with this week what do you so
that's not directly connected to labor
necessarily but the more we follow our
own I think in eternal guidance and just
what do we want our physical bodies to
do what do we want our minds to do what
do you want to learn what do you want to
physically do the more we can create the
technology infrastructure to make that
so easy so that everyone's labored
they're wanting to give to the two right
now the pandemic or to growing food or
to anything that they're seen as a
solution can be easily focused towards
something that's meaningful to them and
so a volunteer coordinating platform
could be something we can absolutely do
with 10,000 people and $100,000 or a
skill sharing platform of hey whatever
the new industries that are going to
emerge out of this are I want to be able
to train in that Howard it can I train a
not without spending a new hundreds of
thousands or tens of thousands of
dollars to training that myself
what
of the other things I think it was
Alejandra who talked about the gig
economy and although right now during
this crisis there is so much the
transportation is still part of the gig
economy right getting goods to people
getting rest getting that stuff made but
the profit doesn't go to the restaurant
and in fact it costs restaurants a lot
to have their food delivered and it
doesn't go to the driver and it doesn't
go to the person using it it goes to
shareholders in uber in TaskRabbit in
all these places creating a platform for
10,000 people focusing on one industry
and saying hey here's our platform for
plumbers or our platform for post
cleaners and coordinating it in a way
that it both brings the the cost for the
the consumer the user down and gives the
worker a higher wage or a higher
resource capacity is what we can do
together and we're not stuffing it off
the profit for for shareholders so if we
had a labor platform where when you're
part of it you're both self-employed
right like I'm my own employee you know
housecleaning for someone else but I can
also tap into a like a union of
self-employed people right we're like
you don't have to go out and find your
work we can find you work you're gonna
clean for all the houses in this
neighborhood on this day so it's more
efficient and you're making 25 bucks an
hour but you're making 25 bucks an hour
right maybe you're paying five bucks a
month to use the platform or something
and so creating it in a way where it
empowers the individual and also we can
solve problems together but there isn't
all this there there's a natural tension
between someone giving the laborer and
someone using the labor but the more
that we can problem solve that together
like hey if you want a house cleaner to
come on your schedule you're gonna have
to pay them a premium but if you can
come on their schedule if you can you
know be in their in your area on Mondays
if you let them clean your house and
Monday you get $1 per hour off or $5 per
hour off and they're not having to do
all this travel time but there's ways to
coordinate labor and bring the cost down
for the person needs the labor and
bringing the hourly wage up for the
person and
I mean our buying power in a way where
you could have medical insurance you can
have dental you can have health you can
have disability you can have all of
these things because you're buying them
together and making sure that we're
we're taking care of one another and
then we already have a four of
foundation of people to coordinate how
do we bring down our cost of living but
that's a little bit the previous section
of like how do we feed ourselves for
less and less money how do we close
ourselves for less and less money which
is the reason we're working but those
are all different solution raisings like
how do we how do we do those things
without needing jobs yeah this very
interesting there I think that like hey
sorry I'm I'm speaking Spanglish now I
just went a Widow's a few Spanish words
and they they are like two things that
could be done and they are very
interesting both of them one is the
volunteer area it's super interesting
because it it helps people do things
that they want to do and they feel that
makes them feel useful and and and has
like an emotional payoff even if there
is no money there is no nothing else
that you get the pay office and you did
something that actually helps and
provides value and that is very
interesting if you can be scalable as
Mark said and with connectors and local
communities because has much more impact
and and much more reach and that's super
interesting to explore and see if that
we time can be transformed into
something that actually also provides a
monetary payoff as well on the other
hand they if you take that in
transforming into something that
actually pays and it's like a collective
that can help workers and labor it would
be a little bit more democratic so they
get they get
and the money that gets paid yet gets
like to the laborer and and there there
are no middleman and taking chunks of
the pay paycheck and things like that
that's super interesting as well it's
the only thing I see there is like it
starts to get into a competition area
like there are some tech platforms that
work like that
all have sort certain features and they
they create these distension that it
could be diffused by by say but not
having sort of an optimizing algorithm
that has like this person has the best
rating and and and creating competition
between people but facilitating the
connections between the ones that has a
task to be done and someone that
actually has the skill and wants to do
that and instead but that as an adjacent
possibly it's very interesting not to
get rid of all the problems but to start
creating a safer environment for for
people so if you go now to a regular
platform like that's where I meet or at
work and then you have to sell yourself
and you have to do all these things and
then that might still be needed but if
you on the other hand can start building
that capital to say okay so if you here
we got to make sure that you have
certain amount of work so it gets sort
of evenly distributed somehow oh that
you get a benefit for then - or like
certain types of insurance so you get
some perks that are not necessarily like
monetary that give you play on this
feeling safe because what we don't have
sometimes is that feeling that is like
you are on your own and belonging to a
platform that a cat or a group that can
help you in that respect I think it
would be super valuable already know
that you just have to go into a platform
and try to get freelance gigs as much as
you can because you cannot plan but easy
give you gives you some peace of mind
that so see some sense of security that
is also already something really
interesting to explore
in these two aspects so two ideas could
be connected as well or drive one into
the other and it comes to my mind the
big disruptions as well in the tech
industry things like Wikipedia that
before you had all the knowledge in
Mexico BDS and botanic ethics like that
a lot sort of people just for free
started adding to these humongous
library and then we we have all this
knowledge is aligning collaboratively we
keep it keep it updated and improve it
so there is something there that people
are willing to do without getting paid
but actually we have a collective payoff
I wonder if there is something there in
the voluntary area that it could also
and have some some impact in the labor
area so if you start doing more more
things get done for free then you need
less money so in any way it's very
simplistic right what I'm saying but but
that's something to consider I've all
very interesting to to explore and I
don't have another idea to add I'm very
I think it's very interesting these two
things that came up my first idea was
also like a platform where we can you
know connect people but I think that the
two dimensions especially the idea of
connectors and amplifying that mark
phone up and and these possibility of
connecting volunteering work and and
unpaid work are very interesting I love
helping cuz I don't know my mine I know
I'm here to help create a world that
works for everyone I know I'm here to
help tech cooperative but I wouldn't
know how to put that into a job
description I wouldn't know how to put
that into what is what do I uniquely
have to offer that could be compared to
somebody else and so help in that help
find you know what is like if you're
running a team and you need a marketer
you need this and you need that like
putting those teams together so then
they can
move forward and create something a
volunteer team of like tackling this
problem and I'm sorry mark are you gonna
say no I was just gonna ask Alejandra if
what she foresaw was a platform that
could possibly grow into those things
and so what when I envisioned it I
envisioned like like a radical
transparency so that people can see
where every dollar is going right and so
if there is if there is competition in a
certain area they would have to also
have this radical transparency and at
some point if if somebody is going to
sign up with somebody being able to see
everywhere where your your dollar is
going would force that would be a
natural attractor for a game be control
of it because I'm gonna go to that
company that's kind of helping the world
better
taking a fair wage and if they're taking
the wages they're taking are too low
they won't be able to survive so I don't
want that I want to be able to I want to
know that they're gonna have enough
money to survive it attract the
expertise without being too radically
selfish but also the the idea that it
could grow into bigger things by saying
maybe this is this is what we need to
connect to so we where we're open to
blending in an open-source way with
somebody who is willing to set up an
insurance plan for us tell us what you
have and we'll try and leverage our
10,000 people
whatever is to give this insurance will
financing or whatever else to meld with
that is I was wondering if that is what
Alejandra you were seeing or is that me
this interpreting now yes I am I also
saw my in my head it requires this total
transparency and because then you have
yeah you see all the mechanisms at work
and what gets paid to where and why and
then then you can be accountable for
everything that happens there so that is
it could be at the level of the sort of
like the person that has a job to offer
or it has to be done and and why is
saying so much for these tasks and
exactly how I do that works that also
could be you such reference that it
could be used for benchmarking and and
say okay this is this is more or less
what as a price regulation in a way what
is the standard for these taxes like
then if something proves to be very
useful then you will also say hey why is
he paying solo then I think what you
said mark it's very interesting when you
take it to a level of a company the
company that is operating like this and
you want them to survive you want them
the rights to be high enough so they can
they they can do well and and you don't
want them to get all the the jobs
because you also want to be able to
distribute them to facilitate the
distribution it's not something that you
have to you can regulate manually and
but that I think that it's also
important that in is part of these being
radical trend radically transparent why
do they the value comes to to the
surface you say more you want them to do
well because they are really providing
value for for with whatever value we
define is so it has to be good for
people
the pain well you have to be responsible
with the environment and I think that is
that a competent loan there is one more
thing that I wanted to say and in that
something that Julie said about the
groups of people task forces of people
that can be put together and that is it
reminded me to the model of some
companies that do functional testing for
example then they have sort of team
leads that work with a lot of people
that are part of the plan that they
can't get paid if they find bugs or they
for a platform it's not necessarily as
the Cure pay but you have a pretty good
chance of making some money if you
participate on test if you are a
certified learning curve and then you
get sort of like the bad that you have
you have this knowledge then you start
getting assignments and you are free to
take them or not taking them and these
team leads are sort of like the enablers
that they also teach you doing that
first period of time where you're sort
of learning the ropes and and that is
something that is another role that it
would be interesting to explore because
these people that can help other people
finding their place in the team so these
same elements like helping how do how do
you present yourself especially in
things that are more tricky like
something that well I'm here to help
connect other people how do i express
that how do I show that and how other
people see that there is value and and
then creating these these themes like
this is this stuff to be done okay so
what do we need for that you define sort
of the initial requirements and then you
gather the people open it up is one
project then next time around it could
be another set of people so this idea of
keeping the rotation open if you have
some sense of security and then you have
some variety then you start getting a
lot of movement and that's that it gets
even more and more interesting as as
more people John
and I know it sounds a little bit maybe
disjointed this a lot of ideas flowing
around here but also I like the idea of
the radical transparency also because it
helps us find niches to problem-solving
as well like especially with the gig
economy and especially with uber and the
delivery ones they don't take into
account that these people have to pay
for gas have to pay mileage or if they
do it's usually below the cost actually
to upkeep their vehicle whereas if we
were able to be transparent in that then
we could both know that you're not
paying enough to this person and also we
could have like mechanics that are at
cost right that are designed to bring
like they're getting paid their labor to
be part of the system and they're like
we can we can coordinate on a higher
level we can bulk my cleaning supplies
if you're a cleaner and you can see is
it environmentally friendly what is we
can crowdsource what is the best cleaner
right what does what do you need less
elbow grease for but is environmentally
friendly and is going to clean this
specific task and sharing the knowledge
to ensure in just doing a lot of the
busy work that a lot like if you're a
house cleaner and you have to mark it
and you have to coordinate and you have
to you know get get this all together
if the backend can do that for you if a
platform is created for you to be able
to do that you can more focus your time
on the actual cleaning and get paid
directly for every hour that your you
are working something just occurred to
me as you were saying that you were
talking about crowdsourcing the cleaning
material so I picture that as getting
input in from people whose opinion you
value and so that by itself has a lot of
power and leverage and it reminded me
that of an idea I tried to vote a long
time ago voice before it's time about
this network green thing the idea that
something could be good for the earth
and financially stable it's in
and part of that was a way to audit
companies because I get auditing for
achieving excellence so I got some
experience in that and auditing can have
like what you would call it that it can
be an attractor like ISO ISO 9000 rice
or whatever it was that they paid people
to come in and audit and they advertised
how they were at that ISO level so that
became an attractor for them to to
create a quality system and to create
processes and have a way of showing them
and protecting you so I am I'm ensuring
that people use them so it would be cool
if this if we could create a space that
wasn't a tractor for kind of an omni
beneficial way of operating so if we
could incorporate into that and publish
a magazine of anybody that had buying
power to say these are the companies
that you should invest in because just
at a plain surface look and their
behavior here is where they think they
rave on this omni beneficial spectrum
but if they are willing to pay for an
auditor we will audit them fairly and
you might come out with the same thing
because audit will be the same price for
everyone it might be lower for smaller
companies yeah that's it it would be
lowered something like that it would
have to be a way that would not could
not be influenced by money and
everything would be asked to be
radically transparent but it could
create an attractor for on the
beneficial behavior by a company by
different companies yeah I'd say like
auditing is something that um
the more transparent you are and the
more willing you're able to speak truth
the bigger advantage it gives you in the
right system in the current system it
doesn't because if you showcase that
you're maybe not as environmentally
friendly as you could be or as socially
just as you could be they don't have
anyone to compare that to say just
assume you're worse than the competition
but in a society where we we the
consumer demands transparency then if
you're not telling the truth and you're
not being transparent we assume worse
than the truth right we'd assume worse
than the competition as opposed to
assuming you're better then right so I
think auditing is a big part that and
it's labor itself like I especially if
we were able to have a algorithm and a
spread sheet system to be able to help
with that that's something I would enjoy
doing is auditing something right and we
could use to do it crowd-sourced
where it's in orabeoni like 5-10 minutes
here and there and you have a thousand
people auditing you instead of one doing
it really in an expert clash and it
could be something that is that is more
volunteer and more just depending on of
course this is what you're auditing and
how complex is yeah yeah I guess when
there there's something to be said for a
thousand opinions dirty there needs to
be a way if we did that to make sure
there most of them were well-intentioned
and and not robots obviously but anyways
it's just just an idea that create an
attractor so this this group that's ten
thousand that could be a thing that they
they do as well is if they ten thousand
people so ten thousand people well
intentioned and so if if if we started
with a hundred and each person brought
in ten from their network and did it
that way you could you couldn't build up
to ten thousand quite easily and then
we assume they're all well-intentioned
then the if if you leverage their
perspectives or their ability based on a
performance scale that you make up to
rate certain companies based on what
their experiences with those companies
then you could produce something that
could be published through those ten
thousand and others that they're
associated with so the reach could be
easily scale up to a million or more and
then that might create the attractors
for the companies to want to be audited
want to change and change their behavior
anyways it's yeah that's all I'm gonna
say about that is anyway we're past the
hour mark does anyone have any closing
statements on what they would like to
say I just wanted to quickly say that
when you talk about going from 100 to
10,000 and then you were like we could
get to a million that actually is the
same factor going from a hundred to ten
thousands which is the doable amount is
the same right you you hundred people
bring in ten people you have a thousand
bring in ten people you have ten
thousand and then of course it goes to a
hundred thousand a million so it's like
the same factor difference and so if you
can get from a hundred to ten thousand
you can get to a million just as easily
either if you have any closing thoughts
before we say goodbye to YouTube no I
think exactly great great exercise all
right do you have any closing closing
thoughts Park I can't even speak anymore
no thank you all right thank you goodbye
YouTube thank you